<module name="model">
<spec id="rhizomatic">CONCEPTUAL SPEC — the main idea of the product. Lives above all implementation specs; changes here have far-reaching consequences.

PROBLEM STATEMENT. Drift detects divergence between specifications and code. Specifications ("specs") declare intended behavior; code markers wrap the lines that implement each spec. Each spec and each marker has a content hash. When a hash changes on either side, the edge between them is "drifted" and a human or LLM agent must review before the baseline is re-established.

Specs themselves cite other specs ("See spec T for the rule this derives from"). Those citations are meaningful: if T's content changes, every spec that cites T may need re-verification. Tracking citations as first-class edges lets drift propagate correctly through the spec graph — without them, edits to a foundational spec silently invalidate every downstream spec without any signal.

THE UNIFIED EDGE. The post-collapse model has ONE edge type. An Edge is a directed relationship between two nodes (specs and/or markers). The From endpoint declares/stores the edge; the To endpoint is the target. Two establishment kinds are encoded by endpoint types:
  - marker → spec (created by `drift link`): the marker stores the edge to the spec it implements.
  - spec → spec (auto-parsed from &lt;ref spec="…"&gt; in spec text): the source spec stores the edge to the spec it references.
The establishment ceremony differs (explicit command vs ambient parse), but the storage and the drift semantics are identical. There is no separate "link" or "ref" type — they are unified under Edge.

NOTATION. We adopt a uniform notation for nodes and edges:
  $ — a spec. $1, $2, $3 are distinct specs.
  # — a marker. #A, #B are distinct markers.
  &lt; , &gt; — directed storage edges. "X &gt; Y" reads: X stores an edge pointing to Y. "X &lt; Y" is the same edge mirrored — Y stores the edge to X.
Worked examples:
  $1 &lt; $2                 — $2 stores an edge to $1. ($2 contains &lt;ref spec="$1"&gt;.)
  $1 &lt; $2 &lt; #A           — equivalent to ($1 &lt; $2)($2 &lt; #A): $2 has an edge to $1; #A has an edge to $2.
  ($1 &lt; $2)($2 &lt; #A)($2 &lt; $300)($300 &lt; $400) — a rhizomatic cluster: $2 has one outbound edge, two inbound edges (#A via link, $300 via ref); $300 is itself pointed at by $400. The leaves are specs ($1, $400); markers are not privileged endpoints.

AXIOMS.
  (A1) DAG over spec-spec edges. The directed graph contains no directed cycles among spec-spec edges: $1 &gt; $2 &gt; $1 is forbidden. Cycles would make the "chain" notion ambiguous and break topological reasoning. (Undirected cycles — paths that return to the start via different edges — are fine and expected in any non-trivial graph.) Marker endpoints cannot participate in cycles because markers are always sources (axiom A2).
  (A2) Storage asymmetry. Markers never have inbound edges. A marker #A may store an edge to a spec (#A &gt; $S) but nothing stores an edge to a marker. Markers are sources only.
  (A3) Rhizomatic edge semantics. Although each individual edge has a storage direction (X &gt; Y means X declared the edge), the SEMANTICS of drift propagation treat the edge as undirected. The graph is rhizomatic, not arborescent: there is no privileged root, no "upstream" or "downstream" orientation, no hierarchy implied by edge direction. A change at any node propagates along edges regardless of which endpoint declared them.
  (A4) Source-of-truth asymmetry. Specs define behavior; code implements. When code changes (marker hash drifts) the spec might still be correct — only the code is suspect, and the review prompt asks "is the code still aligned with the spec?". When a spec changes, every transitively-connected node's alignment is suspect. Concretely: marker hash-drift does NOT propagate; spec hash-drift propagates rhizomatically.

ALGORITHM. Given baseline state B (hashes + edge set at last review) and scan S (hashes + edge set now):
  (i) Edge-set drift. Compare B's spec-spec edges to S's spec-spec edges:
       - in S only  → TodoEdgeAdded     (a new &lt;ref&gt; was declared)
       - in B only  → TodoEdgeRemoved    (a &lt;ref&gt; was deleted)
       Link-style edges (marker → spec) are user-curated and never appear in the scan; their structure drift is handled by the link/unlink commands.
  (ii) Broken edges. For each scan edge (X &gt; Y) where Y does not exist as a node → TodoBrokenEdge. (Typos and dangling refs surface here. Not a fatal scan error — a reviewable todo.)
  (iii) Hash-drift closure. Let C = { specs whose hash differs between B and S }. For each source spec c ∈ C, perform BFS over the undirected spec-spec edge graph. For every visited spec n ≠ c:
          - if no edge resolution covers the (n, c) pair at S's hash of c → emit TodoEdgeDrift{From: n, To: c, SourceSpecID: c}.
          - for each marker m linked to n → emit TodoCascade{From: m, SourceSpecID: c}. Cascade todos are DERIVED: not independently resettable. They clear automatically when the upstream TodoEdgeDrift is resolved.
        Markers linked directly to c are NOT given cascade todos — they are already covered by TodoEdgeDrift on their direct (m, c) edge, and emitting a second todo for the same (marker, source) pair would be redundant.
  (iv) Direct edge drift. Existing pre-collapse algorithm: for each baseline edge, if either endpoint's hash differs between B and S and no edge resolution entry covers the current hashes → TodoEdgeDrift.
  (v)  Marker hash-drift. A marker whose own hash changed produces TodoEdgeDrift on each of its touching edges. It does NOT enter step (iii) — source-of-truth asymmetry.
  (vi) Cycle safety. The BFS uses a visited set; the spec-spec edge graph is a DAG by (A1), but the walk is over the undirected projection and could in principle loop through multi-edge cycles if (A1) were violated. The visited set is the safety net.

RESOLUTION. Each todo resolves with `drift reset`:
  - TodoEdgeDrift(from, to)     → `drift reset from to`           (stamps an EdgeResolution at current hashes; collapses when the edge's endpoints are both re-baselined)
  - TodoEdgeAdded(X, Y)         → `drift reset X Y`               (adds the edge to baseline)
  - TodoEdgeRemoved(X, Y)       → `drift reset X Y`               (drops the edge from baseline and prunes dangling resolutions)
  - TodoBrokenEdge(X, Y)        → not resettable; fix spec text or restore the missing spec
  - TodoCascade(m, c)           → not independently resettable; clears when upstream TodoEdgeDrift(n, c) resolves
The dispatch form is unambiguous: marker shortcodes contain no dots; spec IDs contain exactly one. Two-arg reset with dots in BOTH args is a spec-spec reset; two-arg reset with a dot only in the second is a marker-spec reset; one-arg reset is orphan pruning.

This spec is the contract. Implementation specs (core.validate, core.edge_todo_algorithm, core.rhizomatic_closure, scanner.ref_parsing, orch.reset, pinstore.baselines) describe how the contract is realized; they may be refactored freely as long as the behavior here is preserved.</spec>
</module>
