<module name="principles">
<spec id="friction">Drift intentionally provides no bulk reset. Every drifted edge must be individually reviewed and explicitly resolved. This friction is the core mechanism, not a limitation. A bulk reset would let an LLM blindly mark everything as reviewed without reviewing. The intended workflow — todo, diff --all, reset one edge at a time — forces attention at each edge. Removing this friction would make drift useless as a spec-code sync tool. See cli.no_bulk_reset for the CLI enforcement of this principle.</spec>
<spec id="specs_are_truth">Specs define behavior; code implements specs. When code doesn't match a spec, the code is wrong, not the spec. Validation catches divergence — it is a safety net, not an annoyance. Never weaken a spec or relax validation to accommodate a bug; fix the code. See core.validate for the validation contract.</spec>
<spec id="language_agnostic">Drift works for any text file in any language. The scanner never assumes what you're writing — no extension allowlist, no language-specific logic. Any file that isn't binary (by extension blocklist or null-byte detection) is a valid marker host. This is a design commitment, not a feature: drift must never assume what you're writing. See scanner.text_file_detection for the mechanism.</spec>
<spec id="self_hosting">Drift tracks its own specs and markers. drift todo must be clean before any commit — this is a hard gate, not a suggestion. The project is its own primary test case: if drift can't track itself correctly, it can't track anything. A bug that breaks drift todo on drift's own codebase blocks all other work until fixed.</spec>
<spec id="red_before_green">Reproduce bugs with a failing test before fixing code. Write the test that triggers the bug, confirm it fails for the right reason, then fix the code and confirm the test passes. The failing test is proof you understand the bug before you touch the fix. Never fix a bug without first writing the test that reproduces it.</spec>
<spec id="zero_dependency_portable">Drift has zero external dependencies (Go stdlib only). The release builds a static binary for cross-platform targets with CGO_ENABLED=0 and -trimpath. Install is a one-liner (curl|bash on Unix, irm|iex on Windows) with safety hardening: atomic install, strict checksum verification, no auto-run of unverified binaries, safe tar extraction, path validation. Adoption friction for users is minimized; the installer is held to a high safety bar.</spec>
</module>
