<module name="fileio">
<spec id="session">
Overview: Session is the sole gateway for reads and writes to files under .drift/. A Session holds an exclusive advisory lock acquired at construction and released at Close. The Session abstraction structurally enforces "all .drift/ I/O through one locked handle."

Defined terms:
  Session — see glossary.session
  Begin   — the constructor function; acquires the lock and returns a *Session
  Close   — the release function; idempotent
  Caller  — the function that invokes Begin and is responsible for calling Close

Requirements:
  R1. Begin(dir) MUST acquire an exclusive advisory lock on .drift/state.lock before returning. The lock file MUST be created if it does not exist, and .drift/ MUST be created if it does not exist.
  R2. Begin MUST block until the lock is acquired. There MUST be no implicit timeout; callers needing bounded wait MUST wrap in a context-with-deadline at the call site.
  R3. The lock MUST be released when (a) Close is called, OR (b) the process exits (crash or normal termination).
  R4. Concurrent Begin calls from distinct processes MUST serialize. The implementation MUST NOT silently corrupt state under concurrent invocation.
  R5. Concurrent Begin calls within the same process MUST block on each other. The implementation MUST NOT attempt reentrancy across separate file descriptors of the same lock file.
  R6. Close MUST be idempotent: a second call MUST NOT return an error and MUST NOT release a lock not held by this Session.
  R7. There MUST be no public Lock() method on Session or any other type in package fileio. Lock acquisition is exclusively via Begin. This enforces "all I/O through Session" at the API surface.
  R8. Read and Write operations invoked after Close MUST return an error.

Platform behavior:
  Unix:    lock acquired via unix.Flock(fd, unix.LOCK_EX) on .drift/state.lock
  Windows: lock acquired via windows.LockFileEx with LOCKFILE_EXCLUSIVE_LOCK flag on .drift/state.lock (1-byte range lock)

See also: fileio.read, fileio.write_atomicity, glossary.session, pinstore.load, pinstore.save.
</spec>

<spec id="read">
Overview: Session.Read returns the bytes of a file under .drift/.

Defined terms:
  name — the relative path of the file within .drift/ (e.g. "state.xml", "baselines.bin"). MUST be a direct child of .drift/, not a nested subpath.

Requirements:
  R1. Read MUST NOT take a lock per-call; it MUST rely on the lock held since Begin (see fileio.session.R1).
  R2. Read MUST return an error for which os.IsNotExist reports true when the file is absent. Callers use this to distinguish "fresh project" from "corrupt state" (see pinstore.not_found).
  R3. Read MUST reject the following name inputs with a descriptive error: empty string, ".", "..", any name containing a path separator (os.PathSeparator or '/'), any absolute path.
  R4. Read invoked on a closed Session MUST return an error (see fileio.session.R8).

See also: fileio.session, fileio.write_atomicity.
</spec>

<spec id="write_atomicity">
Overview: Session.Write atomically writes a file under .drift/ via temp-file plus rename. The atomicity property guarantees that a crash at any point leaves either the prior content or the new content at the target path — never a partial write.

Defined terms:
  atomic   — a write is atomic if a crash at any point leaves either the prior content or the new content at the target path, never a partial write
  temp file — the staging file named &lt;target&gt;.tmp in the same directory as the target, written before the rename

Requirements:
  R1. Write MUST NOT take a lock per-call; it MUST rely on the lock held since Begin (see fileio.session.R1).
  R2. Write MUST create .drift/ if it does not exist (via os.MkdirAll on the directory before writing the temp file).
  R3. Write MUST stage the new content at &lt;target&gt;.tmp in the same directory as the target, then invoke os.Rename to atomically replace the target.
  R4. The temp file MUST live in the same directory as the target. Write MUST NOT cross filesystem boundaries (POSIX rename is only atomic within a filesystem).
  R5. If rename fails, Write MUST attempt to remove the temp file (best-effort, errors suppressed) and MUST return the rename error to the caller.
  R6. Write MUST reject names with the same restrictions as Read (see fileio.read.R3).
  R7. Write invoked on a closed Session MUST return an error (see fileio.session.R8).
  R8. Write MUST overwrite any existing file at the target path. There is no append mode.

See also: fileio.session, fileio.read.
</spec>
<spec id="platform_syscalls">
Overview: The platform-specific lock acquisition and release functions translate the cross-platform Session contract (fileio.session) into the actual syscall API of the host operating system. Exactly one of fileio_unix.go or fileio_windows.go is compiled into any given build, selected by Go's build-tag mechanism.

Defined terms:
  lockFileExclusive(f *os.File) — internal helper that acquires LOCK_EX (Unix) or LOCKFILE_EXCLUSIVE_LOCK (Windows) on the given file descriptor; blocks until acquired
  unlockFile(f *os.File)        — internal helper that releases the lock AND closes the file descriptor

Requirements:
  R1. fileio_unix.go MUST be compiled only when GOOS != windows. fileio_windows.go MUST be compiled only when GOOS == windows. The two files MUST never both compile into the same binary.
  R2. lockFileExclusive MUST block until the lock is acquired; it MUST NOT return early with a timeout or "would block" error.
  R3. On Unix, lockFileExclusive MUST call unix.Flock(fd, unix.LOCK_EX). The lock is associated with the open file description; closing any duplicated fd releases the lock.
  R4. On Windows, lockFileExclusive MUST call windows.LockFileEx with the LOCKFILE_EXCLUSIVE_LOCK flag (0x2). The lock range MUST be at least 1 byte starting at offset 0.
  R5. unlockFile MUST release the lock (flock LOCK_UN on Unix; UnlockFileEx on Windows) AND close the file descriptor.
  R6. unlockFile MUST release the lock before closing the fd; if release fails, the fd MUST still be closed to avoid leaking descriptors.

See also: fileio.session.
</spec>
</module>
