<module name="orch">
<spec id="init">Init creates an empty drift.pin file by saving an empty PinState.</spec>
<spec id="todo">Todo loads PinState, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, builds a CoreAlgorithmContext with TodoAction, runs the core algorithm, and returns the EvaluatedState without saving.</spec>
<spec id="reset">Reset loads PinState, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, builds a CoreAlgorithmContext with ResetAction targeting the given marker and spec, runs the core algorithm, and saves the resulting PinState to disk. When specID is empty (single-arg mode), calls ResetOrphan instead.</spec>
<spec id="link">Link loads PinState, scans the filesystem, reconciles, validates that the marker and spec exist, rejects duplicate links, and saves the PinState with the new link appended.</spec>
<spec id="unlink">Unlink loads PinState, finds the link matching the given marker and spec, removes it from Links, also removes any ResolutionState entries for that edge, and saves the PinState. If no matching link exists, returns an error.</spec>
<spec id="reconcile_specs">ReconcileSpecs compares pinned specs against scanned specs. Pinned specs not found on disk are kept in the result with Deleted=true and their baseline hash preserved (no error). New specs in the scan get baseline equal to current hash. Existing specs keep their pinned baseline hash but update filepath and line number.</spec>
<spec id="reconcile_markers">ReconcileMarkers compares pinned markers against scanned markers. Pinned markers not found on disk are kept in the result with Deleted=true and their baseline hash preserved (no error). New markers in the scan get baseline equal to current hash. Existing markers keep their pinned baseline hash but update filepath and line number.</spec>
<spec id="orphan_reset">ResetOrphan takes a single ID. If the ID contains a dot, it is treated as a spec ID; otherwise as a marker ID. If the entry is stale (not on disk, no links), it is removed from drift.pin along with any resolutions. If still on disk, errors. If it has links, errors with guidance to resolve them first.</spec>
</module>
