<module name="orch">
<spec id="init">Init creates an empty .drift/state.xml file by saving an empty State. NOT idempotent: if StateStore.Initialized() reports the project is already initialized (state.xml exists on disk), Init returns ErrAlreadyInitialized without writing. If Initialized() returns a non-not-found error (e.g. corrupt state.xml), Init propagates that error rather than overwriting. See cli.init_idempotent for the user-facing contract. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="todo">Todo loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, builds a CoreAlgorithmContext with TodoAction (propagating baseline Edges and Resolutions), runs the core algorithm, and returns the EvaluatedState without saving. The scan's discovered spec-spec Edges are passed via the Scan struct so the core can detect edge add/remove/broken and propagate rhizomatic closure drift. See principles.friction — review without side effects.</spec>
<spec id="reset">Reset acquires an exclusive state lock for the entire Load→modify→Save window, loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, then resolves a single drifted edge. The (from, to) arguments name the edge endpoints; CLI dispatches based on dots in the IDs (marker-spec for link-style, spec-spec for ref-style). For spec-spec resets, applyRefEdgeReset first reconciles the baseline edge against scan (add if new, drop if removed), and if the To endpoint is missing on disk the action errors with ErrBrokenEdgeNotResettable. The core stamps an EdgeResolution and collapses; the orchestrator then saves the resulting State (including Edges and Resolutions). For removed spec-spec edges, pruneResolutionsTouchingPair drops any dangling resolutions. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="link">Link acquires an exclusive state lock for the entire Load→modify→Save window, loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles, validates that the marker and spec exist, rejects duplicate edges, and saves the State with a new Edge{From: markerID, To: specID} appended (also merging scanned spec-spec edges into baseline via mergeScannedEdges). Writes baseline files for the spec and marker using their current scanned content. The lock prevents concurrent invocations from silently overwriting each other's edges.</spec>
<spec id="unlink">Unlink acquires an exclusive state lock for the entire Load→modify→Save window, loads State, finds the link-style edge matching the given marker and spec, removes it from Edges, also removes any EdgeResolutions referencing the pair in either direction, and saves the State. If no matching edge exists, returns an error.</spec>
<spec id="reconcile_specs">ReconcileSpecs compares baselined specs against scanned specs. Baselined specs not found on disk are kept in the result with Deleted=true and their baseline hash preserved (no error). New specs in the scan get baseline equal to current hash. Existing specs keep their baselined baseline hash but update filepath and line number. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="reconcile_markers">ReconcileMarkers compares baselined markers against scanned markers. Baselined markers not found on disk are kept in the result with Deleted=true and their baseline hash preserved (no error). New markers in the scan get baseline equal to current hash. Existing markers keep their baselined baseline hash but update filepath and line number. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="orphan_reset">ResetOrphan acquires an exclusive state lock for the entire Load→modify→Save window, then takes a single ID. If the ID contains a dot, it is treated as a spec ID; otherwise as a marker ID. If the entry is stale (not on disk, no edges), it is removed from state.xml along with any resolutions touching it. If still on disk, errors. If it has edges, errors with guidance to resolve them first. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="diff">Diff loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, and returns a DiffResult with both spec and marker sides. Each side contains: ID, filepath, line range (markers only), baseline hash (from state.xml), current hash (from scan), baseline content (from BaselineStore), current content (read from disk), HasBaseline flag (false if no snapshot), and Deleted flag (true if entity removed from disk). Read-only — does not modify state. See principles.friction.</spec>
</module>
