<module name="core">
<spec id="validate">Validate must reject duplicate spec IDs, duplicate marker IDs, edges referencing unknown endpoints, self-edges, duplicate edges, directed cycles among spec-spec edges, resolutions referencing unknown endpoints, resolutions on node pairs with no declared edge, or duplicate resolutions. Edges whose endpoint does not exist (broken edges — typically a typo in a &lt;ref&gt; target) are NOT rejected here; they surface as TodoBrokenEdge drift items so the user can fix the spec text or restore the missing spec. Validation must pass when all references are consistent. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="todo_action">Given a TodoAction with a Scan covering all spec and marker IDs, the algorithm runs computeEdgeTodos: TodoEdgeDrift for baseline edges whose endpoint hash differs (no covering resolution); TodoEdgeAdded/Removed for spec-spec edges appearing in only one of {baseline, scan}; TodoBrokenEdge for scan edges whose To endpoint does not exist; rhizomatic-closure TodoEdgeDrift for transitively-reachable specs; and TodoCascade for markers linked to chain-drifted specs. Edges with a matching resolution entry produce no todo. When a node has been deleted (scan hash empty), the corresponding Deleted flag is set. The returned EvaluatedState propagates Edges and Resolutions unchanged. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="reset_action">Given a ResetAction targeting a (From, To) edge, the algorithm records an EdgeResolution with the current endpoint hashes, then collapses all nodes whose every edge is consistent or has a matching resolution. Collapse updates the baseline hash to the current scan hash and prunes resolutions for collapsed edges. When a node's scan hash is empty (deleted), collapse removes the node entirely and filters out its edges. The target edge must be in baseline (either direction) or the action errors. The returned EvaluatedState propagates Edges and Resolutions unchanged. See principles.friction for why reset is per-edge.</spec>
<spec id="collapse">Collapse runs iteratively. In each pass, any node (spec or marker) whose every touching edge is checked gets its baseline hash updated to the current scan hash. When a node's scan hash is empty (deleted), the node is removed and its edges are filtered out. Passes repeat until no node collapses. After all passes complete, resolutions touching collapsed nodes are pruned: deleted nodes get all resolutions pruned unconditionally; non-deleted collapsed nodes get resolutions pruned when the other endpoint is also in sync. Enables progressive collapse across many-to-many edge topologies. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="edge_unchecked">An edge is unchecked when either endpoint's current hash differs from baseline AND no resolution records the current hashes (looked up in either direction — a (From, To) resolution covers a (To, From) edge declaration). If both baseline hashes match the current scan hashes, the edge is consistent and not unchecked. Missing endpoints (already pruned) are treated as having an empty baseline hash. See principles.friction — unchecked edges are the trigger for the review loop.</spec>
<spec id="scan_coverage">The scan must provide a hash for every spec and marker in the context, including empty string for deleted entries. Missing hashes for known specs or markers cause an error. Unknown spec or marker hashes in the scan that are not in the context also cause an error. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="deleted_drift">When a spec or marker is deleted from disk but still in .drift/state.xml, the reconciler keeps it with a sentinel empty-string scan hash. This triggers drift on all touching edges. The Todo struct records the corresponding Deleted flag. After reset, collapse prunes the deleted node and its edges from the result. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="edge_todo_algorithm">computeEdgeTodos is the unified drift-detection entry point. It emits: TodoEdgeDrift for baseline edges whose endpoint hashes changed on either side (with no covering resolution, looked up in either direction); TodoEdgeAdded and TodoEdgeRemoved for spec-spec edges appearing in only one of {baseline, scan} (link-style edges are user-curated and never appear in the scan); TodoBrokenEdge for scan edges whose To endpoint does not exist as a node; and rhizomatic-closure todos for spec-spec edges (chain drift + cascade). Marker hash-drift does NOT propagate (source-of-truth asymmetry). Cycle-safe via visited-set tracking.</spec>
<spec id="rhizomatic_closure">computeRhizomaticClosureTodos propagates spec hash-drift through the undirected spec-spec edge graph. For each changed spec C, walk the graph and emit TodoEdgeDrift for every transitively-reachable spec N (with no covering resolution, setting SourceSpecID to C on the todo), plus TodoCascade for every marker linked to N. The walk uses ONLY spec-spec edges; markers are reached through their linked spec after the walk completes. Markers directly linked to the changed source spec do NOT get cascade todos because TodoEdgeDrift on their direct edge already covers them. Resolutions are looked up in either direction. When (N, C) is already a baseline spec-spec edge, direct-edge drift (step 1 of computeEdgeTodos) handles the spec-spec todo; the closure only emits the cascade todos for markers linked to N in that case.</spec>
</module>
